DEEPAK TIWARI (Application Architect, UI Lead & Developer-Full Stack MEAN/MERN)

Linked In: in.linkedin.com/pub/deepak-tiwari/a0/921/3b/

E-mail: reach.deepaktiwari@gmail.com

Phone No.: +91-9415745215(P),+91-6392251563 (S),+91-9450458358

SUMMARY

- 12 Yrs IT Professional with expertise in Web Application Design & Development on Full Stack MEAN/MERN Technologies.
- Application Architect, Developer/IC, Project/Technical Lead ,SME,CoE Committee Member,EAG Engineer
- TCS Certified ESA(Enterprise System Architecture) Engineer with 93%.
- DataCamp Certified Data Scientist on Python track.
- Top Rank holder out of 560 Teams worldwide in UST Global D3 de Hackathon 2017 and 2018. (Machine Learning +AI)

EXPERIENCE HIGHLIGHTS

Place	Designation	Responsibilities/Nature of Work		Softwares Used.	Exp.
EA Sport	Senior Architect	Salesforce Lead , Engineering Testing Frameworks for Code Coverage and Quality Metrics for SFDX.		SFDX,AWS,ReactJS,Angu larJS1.x,Aura with LTS.Mocha,Sinon and Jasmine	27 th Apr 2019 till Date
UST Global	Application Architect	Application Architect(onsite) –(U.K) – Experian ,Maersk ,Boots Technical Analyst(offshore) - Walmart ,Philips, HighMark Responsibilities		ReactJS ,NodeJS,MongoDB,Angu larJS,HTML 5,ES6,Docker,Webpack, MySQL,RequireJS,Expres sJS,Vue.JS,Angular2+,Ty peScript,Microservices, AWS,Azure,Jenkins,Spri ngBoot	11-Mar-2015 till 24-April2019
TATA Consultanc y Services	Assistant Consultant	Nature of Work Technical Lead, Project Leader & Web Application Designing & Development using Java/J2EE, AngularJS, Bootstrap, Spring and Hibernate. Managed a Team of 18 associates. Responsibilities Technical Lead. Team Building & Maximizing Team Throughput Agile & Reliable Support Process		AngularJS1.0.5, HTML 5, , JavaScript, Java/J2EE, ,Modernizr,RequireJS, Spring 3.x,Hibernate, JSP,Struts,JSF,JSON, XML,Ajax,C/C++	4 th –Aug-2010 till 04-Mar-2015
CDAC Noida	Senior Research Fellow	The nature of work involved Web Application development in Java/J2EE.		Javascript, Java/J2EE ,JSP,Struts,JSF	9 th –Oct–2007 till 1 st –Aug-2010
TOTAL WORK EXPERIENCE			11 YEARS		

CHRONOLOGY OF RECENT PROJECT(S) UNDERTAKEN

COMPANY: Experian, United Kingdom

Responsibilities: -

- Full Stack Application Engineer / Application Architect / Technical Lead / Development / SME / On-Site Lead
- Web-Application System Architect and System Designer focusing on developing huge scalable applications in NodeJS, React JS, AngularJS, Python, MongoDB, HTML 5, ExpressJS, ES6 / MS Typescript frameworks specially NodeJS and its Packages.

Project : DATA PATROL

Project: Beautiful You 1.7

- Experience working with common front-end development tools such as Babel, Webpack, NPM, YARN.
- Working with RESTful API's (JSON/XML Web Services) and GraphQL.
- Working with Git, Stash, Bit Bucket, Web Hooks, and Nexus.
- Experience with SOLID Design Principles of OOPs, Design Patterns like Factory/Observer/Strategy/Proxy and Software Architectural Design Patterns like Layered/Client-Server/Master-Slave/Pipe-filter/Broker/Peer-to-Peer/Event-bus/MVC/Blackboard Pattern.
- ▶ Building Serverless REST API in Node.js & MongoDB App and Dockerising it.
- ▶ Testing AngularJS Apps with Jasmine, Karma, Protractor and React Apps with Jest and Enzyme.
- Handling Authentication in MERN Stack using Bearer Token and Session Cookie.
- Setting up CI/CD Pipeline for Node.JS app with Jenkins.
- Securing Node.JS RESTful APIs with JWT Web Tokens
- Knowledge on Micro-services in Spring Boot, Web Sockets and ReactJS and security using JWT.
- Doing Data Visualization, Text Classification, Sentiment Analysis and building Chatbots using Python.
- Knowledge on Web crawlers and SEO Optimization.
- Optimizing ReactJS Apps and Web Performance.

Description: Experian plc is a consumer credit reporting company. Experian collects and aggregates information on over one billion people and businesses including 235 million individual US consumers and more than 25 million US businesses. In addition to its credit services, Experian also sells decision analytic and marketing assistance to businesses, including individual fingerprinting and targeting. Its consumer services include online access to credit history and products meant to protect from fraud and identity theft.

COMPANY: Boots eCommerce, London, United Kingdom

Responsiilities: -

- Application Architect on Full Stack / Development
- Requirement Analysis, Client Interaction
- SPA Web Application development using
 - ReactJS, ES6+, MongoDB, NodeJS, Docker, Azure, AWS, Jenkins.
- Performance Tuning and SEO Optimization for Website SERP
- Building RESTful APIs, JSON and Multithreaded Web Services.
- Design, Development of Microservices and scale using Message Queues, Spring bot and Kubernetes.
- Build and Deployment with Continuous Delivery using ReactJS, Docker and Microsoft Azure.
- Handling Security, Authentication and Authorization.
- Developing Applications on OOPs SOLID Principles.
- Desgn and Develop applications using SpringBoot + Spring MVC + Spring Security + MySQL
- Working with UX Team to design CSS styles using Layouting/Responsive/Adaptive Design, Specificity and Namespacing.

Description: Boots is the UK's largest pharmacy-led health and beauty chain. Boots UK is part of the Retail Pharmacy International Division of Walgreens Boots Alliance, Inc, the first global pharmacy-led health and wellbeing enterprise.

The Responsibilities were focused in development and maintenance of their Commercial Boots website which offered a catalogue, selection of various products to be bought online from their stores with option for Online Payment Gateways and Step Door Deliveries.

CHRONOLOGY OF RECENT PROJECT(S) UNDERTAKEN....contd....

COMPANY: Maersk – United Kingdom Project: Maersk Line

Responsibilities: -

- Front End Lead and Senior Developer
- Optimization & Benchmarking while developing Application using Full Stack Technologies.
- Responsible for automating the daily operations, monitoring, automated installation, configuration and patching of Linux Application servers, and production application deployment.
- System administration for the entire system development lifecycle in a dynamic data searching, indexing services environment.
- Full Stack Web Application Development using MongoDB, ExpressJS, ReactJS and NodeJS.
- Operationalizing Node.js for Server-side Rendering and Managing Threads in NodeJS.
- Improving Performance in ReactJS and NodeJS.
- > Setting up Continuous Build and Deployment and Delivery using Jenkins, Docker and Azure.
- Setting up Authentication for Node.js and MongoDB for a ReactJS App.
- Working with APIs using Flask, FlaskRESTPlus and SwaggerUI.
- Working with AngularJS 1.5, Webpack, Node and Spring Boots.
- Resolving cross-browser/platform issues
- Developing dash boarding or charting applications on responsive web / mobile.

Description: Maersk Line, is the largest operating unit in A.P. Moller–Maersk by revenue and staff. Maersk is structured into two main business segments: transport & logistics and energy. These two branches include several subsidiaries such as container shipping and related activities. "Container shipping and related activities" is the largest business area for A.P. Moller–Maersk, providing almost half of the group's revenue in 2008. It comprises worldwide container services, logistics and forwarding and terminal activities under the brand names: Maersk Line, Safmarine, and Damco.

PROJECT: Disrupt & Move from Reading to Remembering by adding Self-teaching/mentoring capability and gamification to eLearning systems using Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning.

Company: UST Global

Public URL: https://deepak-tiwari-ilearn.netlify.com

Responsibilities:

- This project I made as part of D3 Hackathon in which I participated and got top10 rank out of 560 Teams worldwide.
- ▶ Team Size -1
- **DURATION:** 3 Months (SELF OWNED)

Environment: RESTful Architecture/MEAN Stack

- AngularJS 1.0.5/Bootstrap 2.2.2.
- RequireJS/HTML 5/CSS3
- ExpressJS/MongoDB
- NodeJS,Bower,Grunt,Gulp
- Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning

Project: UST D3 Hackathon 2018.

Themes: Interfaces

Description: The project can be successfully deployed across Accounts in organization where it can be used by Technical Leads/Manger/Architects to mentor the students, set up Exit criteria's and keep refining the Account level technical needs and standards. The application is built on Al/ML framework which adds another dimension to the application through inbuilt systems like **iMentor** and **iRecall2Predict** which defines career path to associates and suggests them courses and adds gamification to the app by telling them of their performances as well. *It uses the concept like Sentiment Analysis ,Full Text Search ,Recommender Engine ,Automatic Quiz Creation , Web Scraping the Wiki Pedia content , Chat bots etc.*

EDUCATION, TRAINING & CERTIFICATION

EDUCATIONAL SUMMARY

Exam/Degree	Year of Passing	Name of Institute/ Board/University	Percentage of Marks in aggregate and Division
Class X	2000	I.C.S.E	89% (1st Div)
Class XII	2002	I.S.C	75% (1st Div)
B.Tech (CS & IT)	2007	I.E.T , M.J.P Rohilkhand University ,Bareilly	7.1 D.G.P.A [71% (1st Div)]

TRAININGS

- 1. Training at PNB Institute of Information Technology, Lucknow for Advanced Java and J2EE Technologies.
- 2. Received 4 months Training in Siemens SIEMENS as Graduate Trainee on their Office Automation Solution.
- 4. MEAN Stack Web Developer Training from Udemy.
- 5. React+Redux Training from Udemy

CERTIFICATIONS

- Java Certified Engineer from Cambridge Certification Authority CCA CAMPRICATION AUTHORITY
- Python Developer from Data Camp
- Machine Learning Engineer from Data Camp
- Data Scientist from Data Camp ②
- TCS Certified ♣ Engineer on Enterprise Architecture Design Principles. Score 93%.
- JavaScript (ES6/7) and CSS3 Certified Professional from SoloLearn. SOL©LEARN

AWARDS/APPRECIATIONS

- Received Synergy Award from TCS Executive V.P for Implementing Critical Process Change.
- Received Best Production Support Team Award for FY '13 in TCS.
- Appreciation Note from TCS Senior Management for Flawless System Performance & Improved Concurrency for FY'13.
- Consistently ranked A and promoted to positions of higher responsibility within TCS.
- Received (S) miles award for being part of TCS Technical Recruitment Panel for various Campus and Off Campus hiring.
- Received CLP Faculty Award in TCS for mentoring associates on AngularJS, REST and Performance Tuning.
- > Rank 5 holder among 560 Teams worldwide in UST D3 Hackathon '17 (15 (Theme- Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning).
- Top -10 Rank Holder among 700 Teams worldwide in UST D3 Hackathon '18. (Theme Interfaces).